<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Juries justified: or, A word of correction to Mr. Henry Robinson; for his seven objections against the trial of causes, by juries of twelve men. /  By William Walwin. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E618_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E618[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Juries justified: or, A word of correction to Mr. Henry Robinson; for his seven objections against the trial of causes, by juries of twelve men. /  By William Walwin. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Wood; and are to be sold at his house, near the Flying-Horse in Grubstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Robinson, Henry.  Certain considerations in order to a more speedy, cheap, and equall distribution of justice throughout the nation.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664? --  Certain considerations in order to a more speedy, cheap, and equall distribution of justice throughout the nation.</term>
               <term>Jury --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law reform --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justice, Administration of --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JURIES juſtified: OR, A WORD OF CORRECTION TO M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. HENRY ROBINSON; <hi>FOR</hi> His ſeven Objections againſt the Trial of Cauſes, by Juries of twelve men.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WALWIN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job. 22.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remove not the ancient Land-mark which thy Fathers have ſet.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Wood;</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe, near the <hi>Flying-Horſe</hi> in <hi>Grubstreet.</hi> 1651.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116066:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116066:2"/>
            <head>Juries Juſtified: <hi>OR,</hi> A Word of Correction, to Mr.
<hi>Henry Robinſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough a ſilence had seiz'd me, equal to his that was born and continued dumb, till his father was in danger of being murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet retaining ſtill a ſincere and vigorous affection to my Native Countrey, and ſeeing this mans Knife offering at the throat of our preſervers (ſuch I eſteem our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) for <hi>Englands,</hi> and for this its fundamental effen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial liberty, I could not hold my peace; but muſt tell M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <hi>Robinſon,</hi> he deals moſt injuriouſly with his Country, whereof he muſt either ſpeedily repent, or be made aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: For how doth it appear,
<hi>That there is not a competent number of underſtanding and fit men to be had in the leſſer diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a County, for trial of all cauſes upon all occaſions?</hi> which is his first frivolous objection. If by lesser Divisions, he means Hundreds, who doth not know it to be a moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſlander? there being not the leaſt in <hi>England,</hi> but affordeth a double competency of underſtanding and fit men; yea, ſhould he mean Pariſhes, I verily beleeve, a <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116066:3"/>sufficiency might even there be found, for trial of all the cauſes of each Pariſh; but that needs not, the diviſions of Hundreds being more commodious, and the Hundred Courts being of ancient continuance, might ſoon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the former use; in which Courts (before the Conqueſt) <hi>all cauſes or matters in queſtion, upon eſpecial penalty were finally to be decided, in every Month.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerour</hi> was ſo unjuſt and unworthy (indeed ſo perjured) as to alter this courſe ſo far, as to ordain that four times in the year, for certain days, the ſame busineſſes ſhould be determined in ſuch place as he would appoint, where he conſtituted Judges to attend for that purpoſe, and others, from whom (as from his own boſom) all litigators ſhould have juſtice, from whom was no appeal; and appointed others for the puniſhment of malefactors: yet he never attempted to take away Juries, as finding by the reſolute ſtrugling of the people againſt what he did, that they would never bear it. So as this M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robinſon</hi> does what he can, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the preſent Parliament, to deal worſe with us then the Conquerour did with our Predeceſſors not minding as it ſhould ſeem, how heinous an offence it hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways judged, for any to endevour the ſubverſion of the fundamental Laws of the Nation: nor regarding how frequently this Parliament have avowed to maintain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable, thoſe fundamentals, in all things touching life, liberty, and eſtate, with all things incident thereunto; ſo as he invites them to do that, then which nothing could be more diſhounourable. Inſomuch, as it is a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing to conceive, whence it is that he ſhould engage himself in ſuch a ſubject, nor can I imagin; except it be from his proneneſs to invention, a humour for the moſt part got by travel, but proving very unhappy to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as might be inſtanced, in our exchange of many of our subſtantial honest plain cuſtoms, for Frenchified and Italianated inventions, which have had no ſmall ſhare in our late diſtempers, new platforms of Government, ſent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116066:3"/>Engliſh-fugitives abroad, to reduce us into the like depth of bondage with our neighbours, having been received with too great applauſe; but it is ſtrange the ill ſucceſs of the inventers &amp; attempters, few of which have eſcaped exemplar puniſhment, ſhould not as Land-marks warn travellers from ſuch Shipwracks. And of all our Engliſh travellers (I ſay) well fare Col. <hi>Henry Marten,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned a true Engliſh-man, and continued ſo ever after; always manifeſting a moſt zealous affection to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries liberties, and eſpecially to this, of Trials by 12 men or Juries; as eminently appeared by his demeanor upon the Bench at <hi>Redding,</hi> where it being his lot to give the charge to the Grand-Jury, in the firſt place, he wiſht them to be rightly informed of their own place and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, affirming it to be judicial, when as their owne (meaning the Juſtices) was but miniſterial; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired them not to ſtand bare any longer, but to put on their hats, as became them, and not to under-value their Country, which virtually they were; or words to this effect: which I the rather mention, to set traveller againſt traveller; for had he been a meer country Juſtice, and not ſeen the world abroad, this our Anti-Juriman, poſſibly would have ſaid it had been a vapour, ſutable to one that had never been farther then the ſmoke of his own Chimney; for ſo our inventive innovating travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, use to ſilence thoſe that oppose their corrupt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings: And I have good hope our fear is our greateſt harm, for certainly the Honourable Parliament would never have referred the care of the Regulating of Law and its proceedings, in ſo ſpecial a manner to Colonel <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> but that they approve of his affection to Trials
<hi>per</hi> Juries.</p>
            <p>But it may be, he lays the moſt weight of his firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection upon the word <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> that <hi>there is not a competent number of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and fit men:</hi> Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed is very good, but as I take it, there is not ſo great a want thereof in
<hi>England,</hi> as there is of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116066:4"/>a faculty that puts on to the doing of what is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to be ones duty, and to the reſiſtance of what is not: a little quantity whereof (in my opinion) were very wholeſom for one that is troubled with the riſing of ſuch Objections. But as for underſtanding ſufficient to judge between right &amp; wrong, in any caſe, where proof is to be made by witneſſes openly and freely to be examined, and where a man ſhall be ſure to have the help of eleven more equally engaged under oath to be careful therein; truly I wonder, that (any man not ſuſpicious of his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or not over-weening it) ſhould ſo much as doubt, that a competency of ſuch underſtand fit men, are not in every leſſer Diviſion or Hundred to be found.</p>
            <p>Indeed, underſtanding is in great reputation; and ſo is utterance too, but yet nothing is ſo precious as a true conſcience; not ſuch a one as is ſatisfied with, <hi>touch not, tast not, handle not;</hi> nor with ſaying <hi>Corbun:</hi> nor with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of days and times, no nor with saying <hi>Lord, Lord;</hi> but with doing judgment and juſtice, in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Captive, and ſetting the Oppreſſed free; in feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hungry, clothing the Naked, viſiting the Sick and the impriſoned; and in faithfully keeping all promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and compacts amongſt men, without which civil ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties cannot be maintained.</p>
            <p>And certainly, any one that hath ſuch a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would make a Conſcience of removing ſo ancient a Land-mark, which our fore-fathers have set, <hi>Job.</hi> 22.28. and more of ſuch good Conſcience I beleeve are to be found amongſt our ancient Engliſh Gentry, and other our Free-holders, than among our ſharp-ſighted, ſmooth tongued Travellers; and ſuch as (to the honour of our Engliſh nation) have in all time ſerved their Country juſtly and faithfully, judging the cauſes both of rich and poor without fear of favour, as juſtly as can be expected amongſt men, yea, without reſpect to perſons or opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as truly honouring God in their hearts, and tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at an Oath taken to deal juſtly; and who with <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116066:4"/>their live and fortunes, all times, have preſterved <hi>this,</hi> the moſt eſſential Liberty of England.</p>
            <p>For howſoever men in theſe days make bold to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<hi>Magna Charta</hi> under their feet, making ſport at the many abſurd prerogative and superſtitions things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained; it is to be noted, that theſe things are but as a French garb or cloathing, which the Conqueror and his ſucceſſours, by main ſtrength, forced our fore-fathers to put on: but yet, as an Engliſhman is to be known from a Frenchman amongſt a thouſand, though he labor to faſhion himſelf as the moſt Frenchified Gallant; ſo are our true Engliſh Liberties, contained in <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> as eaſie to be differenced from amidſt that ſuperſtitious and in ſome meaſure, tyrannical heap eaſt upon them, the late King, culled out to purpoſe, and reduced into that excellent Law (as this parliament ſtiled it ſince his death) the <hi>Petition</hi> of
<hi>Right,</hi> and wherein trials <hi>per</hi> Jurles is the principal.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is a ſtrange kind of ſervice or grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the Parliament in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> for ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable places and favours conferred upon him, to invite them to take away Junes, and to erect another way of trial of Cauſes, whereby he muſt neceſſarily render them more odious to the people, that the worſt of thoſe they have removed: for certainly, had either party when theſe publick differences began, propoſed the taking away of Juries, they had never had a thouſand men to have taken part with them; ſo as if his counſel ſhould take place, I wonder where the parliaments Cauſe would be, which they have ever, hitherto, held forth, for the concurrence of the People? is it not alſo as eaſie to judge for whom he labours to beget friends, by his ſo doing, it being no new thing with him to play the Lapwing.</p>
            <p>As ill alſo doth he repay the Army; for whereas they publiſh to all the world; That they eſteemed all preſent enjoyments (whether of life or livelihood, or nearſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,) <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116066:5"/>a price but ſufficient to the purchaſe of ſo rich a bleſſing, <hi>viz.</hi> That they, and all the free-born people of England might ſit down in quiet under their own vines, under the glorious Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and Righteouſneſs, and in full poſſeſſion of thoſe
<hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Rights and Liberties, without which, they could have little hopes to enjoy either any comforts of life, or ſo much as life it ſelf, but at the pleaſure of ſome men, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling meerly according to Will and Power.</p>
            <p>What more fundamental liberty than the trial of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by Juries of twelve men? What more conſtant, more glorious adminiſtration of Juſtice and Righteouſneſs? Yet this true or falſe lover of the Army, inſinuates, nay, invites the taking of this away, as the end of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, as if they had conquered, not for the eſtabliſhment of our fundamental liberties, but for their extirpation: it theſe are his
<hi>mites</hi> he ſo much boaſts of, to caſt into the work of Reformation, ſure it is not for the Engliſh, but the Scotch Treaſury; where is he ſhould be as acceptable as (time was) one was at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> the new Office of Addreſſe may ſerve turn for private parties, with any body, and is a fit contrivance for him to be <hi>hic &amp; ubique</hi> as formerly: What think yee of it? is it, or is it not? Is it not more likely, than that <hi>England</hi> ſhould not be able to afford a ſufficient number of judicious and conſcionable men for Juries? for my part I profeſſe I think it is.</p>
            <p>And how I pray doth it appear, that <hi>People are generally unwilling to be called upon for Jurie-men, whereby they neglect their own affairs?</hi> which is his ſecond objection. What an unheard of grievance hath this tender hearted man found out! even the moſt inſenſible burthen of ſerving upon Juries; wherein his care appears above and beyond all that ever petitioned the Parliament: not one Petition of the well-affected, in all their large Petitions, ſo much as minding or deſiring to have it removed; no, nor none of the ill-affected: manifeſtly ſhewing, that either he is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116066:5"/>better then the beſt, or worſe then the worſt affected: ſay Scotch, or Engliſh, whether is it? (for he deſires us to be tried by God and his Country) is it not right ſteeling. But certainly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <hi>Robinſon</hi> is troubled, the plain people ſhould be put upon occaſions to underſtand themſelves in any meaſure, or be able to diſcern of one anothers cauſes, but would have them ſo wholly fixt upon their own particular affairs, that they might remain as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the laws of the land, as in time of Popery they were of the laws of God; then, knowing no more but what the Prieſt pleaſed: and now he would have them put all their underſtandings (in the affairs of law) into the pockets of ſuch Judges, as he in his own brain fancies, and would perſwade them to it for their own good, then they might the better follow their more profitable cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; he finding, it ſeems that every man is born for himſelf, and not ſo much as a Jury-mans time to be ſpent for the publique: ſure 'twill not be long but he will alſo find, Conſtables, Headboroughs, and all other Officers to their hands; but by the way, not without good pay, for ſo he carefully propoſeth for his Judges, and ſo large as they may live upon it when they are out of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and thus he will deviſe waies to raiſe monies in ſuch ſort I warrant ye, as ſhall be no waies burthenſome to the people, no ſo much as felt by them, if you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him, but ſo long till he hath brought you into his fooles Paradice, when he hath you there, beleeve or no, all is one, he will make you pay, and ſay too you feel it not; to ſuch an end drives his Mountebank pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in all he hath yet undertaken; for he hath made ſome believe, that he will ſhew how all the vaſt charges of the Common-wealth ſhould be conſtantly defrayed without burthen to the the people; but ſure his meaning is, that he would have them at ſuch a paſſe, as they ſhould not dare to ſay the contrary, if he but ſay it is ſo: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; where are the mountains he hath ſo often promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, are they in his office of addreſſe, or are they not?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116066:6"/>'tis like there's more, then ſuch as truly love the Liberties of their Country can imagin.</p>
            <p>Well, all the Jurie-men in England ſhall be excuſed from any further ſervice, <hi>becauſe they are generally unwilling:</hi> off with your hats, Country-men, and thank him; he onely takes care of you and your affairs: Not a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment man, God be prayſed, hath had this wicked care of you, as for a poor complement, a little drawing back from your duty, to take you at your words, and ſmile you out of all your liberties at once; for beleeve it, loſe this and loſe all: No more complements, I beſeech you; but upon the firſt call, pack up and be going, for if once M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
<hi>Robinſon</hi> take you napping, he may chance ſhew you a new
<hi>Florentine trick</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>For he further objecteth, that <hi>though they do come to avoid the penaltie, they ſeldome take the courſe to be rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and fitted to judge of the matter in controverſie.</hi> But doth it appear to be a truth, that they come (only) to avoid the penalty? it may be ſome do ſo, &amp; yet they may bring their conſciences with them; (which, ſome think, have been as frequently found under Felt Hats and Worſted Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as with people of a finer Stuff,) and then I hope, it is well they are there; but that one Swallow ſhould make a Summer, or one Woodcock a Winter, is againſt our Engliſh proverb; and as ill reaſoning it is, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (as he doth) that none come, but to avoid the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when as it is impoſſible for him to know it, or to think it, ſo as to beleeve it: but ſome ſay, our decoy Ducks may twattle any thing, for what is this and all the reſt but twatling?
<hi>They ſeldome take the courſe to be rightly qualified and fitted to judge of the matter in controverſie,</hi> What courſ trow hath he ſeen beyond the ſeas in his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, that are wanting here? are not our Juries and Jurie-men ſufficiently known before hand, who ſhall be upon this, and who upon that cauſe, that the parties concerned might apply themſelves to them by great let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and gifts, to make them ſenſible? what a horrible
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116066:6"/>defect is this, and it ſeems would be perfectly ſupplied by ſuch Judges as he fancies; then indeed they might be rightly qualified to judg, as ſhould be beſt for their own and their Patrons advantage: And truly, in this way ſure he ayms to be a Judg himſelf, and no doubt would ſoon come to have a feeling of the Cauſe; but if he do, I hope his itch will not yet be cured, and that he ſhall ſcratch where it doth not itch, firſt, as he hath done for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; though now provender prick him to ſpur-gal his Country, as now he doth.</p>
            <p>For yet again he ſticks them in the ſides, with this; That,
<hi>Most commonly, one or two active and nimble-pated men over-ſway all the rest of the Jury; and too often for the worst:</hi> which is his 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Objection. But truly, with us in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> our nimble-pated men are not in ſo great credit, as poſſibly they are in other parts, we are generally of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a more dulliſh complexion, which renders moſt ſo conſiderate as to ſuſpect thoſe few nimble-pated men as are amongſt us; and for the moſt part not without cauſe: ſo as the nimble-pated ſeldom carry any thing, except they have reaſon and equity of their ſide, and then the more they ſway therewith the better: And thoſe <hi>dull</hi> men (as he accounts them now it ſervs his turn) were he to deal with them in buying, ſelling, letting or ſetting, I beleeve he would not think them ſo eaſily caught with Chaff or Nut-ſhels: Nor is right and wrong ſo difficult to be diſcerned in Cauſes and Controverſies, but that an ordinary capacity (careful to keep a good conſcience, and that is tender of an oath) ſhall ſoon perceive the true ſtate thereof; and be able to do right therein accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to evidence: Nor will this nimble-pated M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> with all his quickneſs of wit, be able to make this (the moſt deſperat project he ever undertook, or was ever offered at in
<hi>England</hi>) paſs for currant Coyn with our dulleſt apprehenſions; and in time may be made to know, that none are ſo apt to miſtakes as the quick-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; nor any ſo ſottiſh, as thoſe that are conceiptedly wiſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116066:7"/>
            <p>Another gird he gives <hi>Our goodmen and true,</hi> is; That,
<hi>Though never ſo many of them diſſent in judgment from the rest, they must notwithſtanding all concur in the Verdict, or be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into it;</hi> which is his 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Objection: And truly (how ſtrong ſoever he beleeves it) nothing in my opinion is more commendable in the inſtitution of Juries, than the proviſion that all muſt agree, and agree neceſſarily and finally in ſo ſhort a time; for ſhould it reſt on a major part, there might be ſome won for partiality, and ſome won for complaint in the parties againſt whom the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict is given; and ſome cauſe of quarrel ever after amongſt the Jury-men themſelvs: but in that all 12 muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, all theſe miſchievous inconveniences are manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be avoided; and in that it is provided that they muſt make an end before they ſhall either eat or drink, it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth (what is ſaid before) that right and wrong are not hard to be diſcerned, and that thoſe that are convinced of the truth and yet deſire to carry it otherwiſe, wanting that ſtrength of a good conſcience, to bear them out in ſuch a ſtrait of time, will yeeld to the truth rather than die in it; which thoſe that labour to keep a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, even dare to die: beſides, had they further time, what means would be un-aſſayed to corrupt their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict? So as all things juſtly conſidered, doubtleſs it is the beſt proviſion that ever was in the world.</p>
            <p>But he hunts farther to finde matter againſt them, and hath found; <hi>That if they give corrupt or erroneous Verdict, there cannot justly be any penalty inflicted on them, becauſe they may pretend, they did at first declare themſelves unfit for ſuch employment; that they undertook it not willingly, but were compelled thereunto:</hi> This is a long-winded Objection. But (if any part of it were true, as I do not ſee it is) may they not juſtly be unfit for a corrupt Verdict? what a vaſt difference is there in judgment between our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and ſome of their white ſons? They no doubt, in the time of the inſtitution of Juries, fore-ſaw as much as this man objects, and yet provide the moſt heavie <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116066:7"/>and reproachful puniſhment for a falſe Verdict, found <hi>per</hi> Attaint, as ever the wit of man deviſed; As, that every one of their Houſes ſhould be razed to the ground, their Trees ſtockt up by the roots, and all their Ground turn'd up and made uſeleſs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And all this juſtly too, as being fully convinced, it could not be, except it were wilfully and wickedly done, and deſerving to bee made exemplary; and is ſo good a proviſion againſt corruption, that very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath ſuch a caſe befaln: but either men have had conſciences for right; or have been deterred from da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be confederates in ſo high a wrong, as to give a falſe or corrupt Verdict; as knowing it in vain to ſay in excuſe, as this man goes on: <hi>That they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took it unwillingly, and were compelled thereunto; and when they ſaw there was no avoiding it, they endeavoured to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed therein according to the uprightneſs of their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if they be thought to have done amiſs, it was but what they could not remedy, and are heartily ſorry for it.</hi> Such Childiſh toyes, as fitter for Children than men, were of no value with them; and therefore ſuppoſing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, a Man, and bound to ſerve his Country in any place as he ſhall be lawfully called thereunto (wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or unwilling) and to diſcharge his truſt judiciouſly and faithfully, or to ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>His laſt Objection is; That, <hi>The keeping the Jury without Fire-light, Bread, or Drink, as the Law requires, may poſſibly make the major part of them, if not all, agree upon a Verdict contrary to their Conſciences, to be freed from any of theſe exigencies; at least, ſome of them to ſtrike up with the rest in a joint-Verdict, ſince it is well near impoſſible for twelve men, all circumſtances conſidered, much more in a doubtful caſe, to bee of one opinion; and though the caſe were never ſo clear, yet one peremptory man of a ſtrong conſtitution, whether his judgment be right or wrong, may ſterve all the rest, unleſs they will give Verd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct as he will have them.</hi> Certainly, he thinks moſt men of ſuch a <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116066:8"/>kinde of tenderneſs in conſcience, as ſoon is crackt a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; beleeve it Sir, a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſcience is of more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ſtuff, and will endure every one of theſe, yea death it ſelf, rather then be ſo baſe and unworthy; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but from unworthineſs could not be ſuppoſed: For if a man were but reſolved how baſe a thing it were ſo to do, how could he once think of <hi>ſtriking</hi> up with the reſt, in a joint falſe Verdict (conſcience in this caſe being more powerful then the ſtrongeſt conſtitutions?) And as for any abſurdity in their being kept without <hi>fire-light, &amp;c.</hi> it ſuppoſes that they have had time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at the Trial (or might have had) to be fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from the examination of the Witneſſes, in the right ſtate of the Cauſe; which then they are to look to, and to clear all their ſcruples by what queſtions they pleaſe, and well to underſtand themſelves and one another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they diſcharge the Witneſſes or go together: And this ſtanding for good, what cauſe is there they ſhould have any longer time then is admitted them? Except to to make them liable to corruption.</p>
            <p>For my part, I have heard many diſcourſes touching Juries, but never any material exception againſt the way of Trials by them: Indeed I have heard divers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and wonder, that the way of proceeding before Cauſes come to Juries, ſhould be ſo tedious, ſo full of charge, trouble, and perplexity; ſince in their accompt, there is very little more requiſite in any Cauſe, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time for preparation and appearance, as about a Month or two; and then one chief Officer (a Judg or the like) Witneſſes, and a Jury, and time for Trial, and ſo an end: A diſpatch as ſpeedy, with leſs charge, and more certainty, than any new thing propoſed by this new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor; moſt of the accuſtomed pleading, ſerving ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perplex then clear the Cauſe to the underſtanding of the Jury: Which ocaſioned that at a certain Trial (time was) after the ſtate of the Cauſe was ſet forth in the Declaration (the Councel beginning to ſpeak) the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Jury, cals to the Judg and tels him, he had an <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116066:8"/>humble ſuit to his Lordſhip; well (ſays the Judg) what is it? My Lord (ſaid he) it is; that now the ſtate of the Cauſe hath been ſet forth, we may proceed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the examination of Witneſſes, and ſo to give our Verdict, whil'ſt we remember what is material, and that we may ſpare the labour of theſe Gentlemen the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel on both ſides, whom I ſee are prepared to ſpeak large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto; for truly (my Lord) if they ſhall fall to work as they uſe to do, our underſtandings will be ſo confounded by their long diſcourſes, and many niceties, as we ſhall not be able ſo rightly to judge thereof as now we ſhall, this was his humble motion; but the Judg ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly been a Pleader, laught at the honeſt man, and ſo did all the Court, except ſome plain people that had ſo little underſtanding as to think there was reaſon in it. But ſuch was the ſport of thoſe times, and perhaps may make ſome merry now, but yet they may conſider that mocking is catching, and that laughter oft ends in Lachrymae. 'Tis but a ſtory, yet a true one, and may one day be acted to the life, and with a general applauſe, ſo it be well and throughly done: And do this man what he can, the many good mens lives and eſtates, that have been preſerved by Juries, will never be forgotten whil'ſt <hi>England</hi> is <hi>England;</hi> and wherein I deem my ſelf ſo much concerned, as in gratitude I juſtly owe my Country this ſervice; but have done it gently, as judging gentle <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> to be the beſt; and the rather, becauſe the Object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or is of my acquaintance, which made me indeed unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to undertake him, left it might be deemed diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to friendſhip; but ſeeing no body elſe did, and ſince he knew my minde to be againſt his Propoſitions, and much more againſt his endeavour to deprive us of our <hi>Juries,</hi> and yet would publiſh them, to the prejudice of Common Right, (againſt which in all his writings he hath uttered moſt irradicating expreſſions) I take it, this <hi>Word of Correction</hi> is properly beſtowed on him; and I hope profitably for the Common-wealth, having indeed <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116066:9"/>been born withall too long: for whil'ſt the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſleep, envious men will be ſowing their Tares.</p>
            <p>To Correct all the reſt of the errours in his little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, were an endleſs labour; nor will this my preſent la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour (I hope) be abſolutly needful, for certainly Juries cannot in time of Parliament b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in any danger; and then, they ſtanding, his project fals: Only I thought it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to appear a friend to this my Countries principal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, when any one ſhould adventure to appear ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable an enemy; wiſhing with all my heart, that hee may conſider the nature of what he hath done, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that as there was a Law (amongſt the <hi>Locrines</hi> I take it) that he that moved to have any new Law eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſhould appear as if he were going to Execation, and if that he moved were not approved, he was indeed to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer: Even ſo among us, there is a Law called the <hi>Exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mengement,</hi> wherein all are accurſed, that ſhall move for any Law to be made, contrary to our ancient Rights; and to ſubvert the Fundamental Law, hath been always adjudged a capital offence; and though with help of a little Faſting-ſpittle, a man may play with Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, yet 'tis a fond thing to take fire into ones boſom, and venture upon a charm only to keep it from burning. It were much better to pray unto God to give no more wit, nor ſtrength, nor power, than men have good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to make a right uſe of, to his glory, and their ſpiritual good: Which is and ſhall be ever, the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Walwin.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
